<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The only deliverer from wrath to come, or, The way to escape the horrible and eternal burnings of Hell By Thomas Vincent.</title>
            <author>Vincent, Thomas, 1634-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V446C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43945</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476394</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2258:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The only deliverer from wrath to come, or, The way to escape the horrible and eternal burnings of Hell By Thomas Vincent.</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Thomas, 1634-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Calvert, and Samuel Sprint, and are to be sold at the Golden Ball ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, Unversity of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151431:1"/>
            <p>The only DELIVERER FROM Wrath to Come: OR, The Way to eſcape the horrible and Eternal Burnings of HELL. By <hi>Thomas Vincent,</hi> Sometime Miniſter of <hi>Maudlins Milk-ſtreet, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Calvert,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Sprint,</hi> and are to be Sold at the Golden <hi>Ball</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:151431:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151431:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Theſ. 1.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Part of the 10th. Verſ.</hi> Even Jeſus which delivered us from the Wrath to Come.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>PAſt pains may eaſily be forgotten, future pains are not eaſily believed, preſent pains in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity are ſo grievous and afflictive, that all the Wealth and Honour in the World cannot countervail them; and O how welcome is ſuch a Phyſitian, who can give eaſe and remove them! But did people believingly apprehend what horrible pains and torments the wicked muſt endure, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Flames of Hell-fire, where they can have no eaſe, and their miſery ſhall have no end; did they apprehend how fearful a thing it is to fall into the hands of the Living God, and to be ſwallowed up by his Wrath, which hath all ſuch, who are out of Chriſt, in the purſuit; and which will certainly come, and may quickly ſeize upon them, ſurely they would uſe their uttermoſt diligence now to eſcape, ſurely they would with the greateſt inquiſitiveneſs ſeek out now for a place of refuge, from the fiery Tempeſt of Gods Vengeance; and this Text which maketh a diſcovery of <hi>the only Deliverer from the Wrath to Come,</hi> would found with moſt tranſcendent ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their ears, and the glad tidings thereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what Jeſus hath done for his People, would above all things be moſt welcome unto their Hearts. <hi>Even Jeſus who delivered us from the Wrath to Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151431:3"/>
            <p>In the former Verſe, the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> what manner of entrance he had at firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and what the great effect of his Miniſtry was upon them; namely, that they were converted thereby; which converſion of their's he ſets forth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By the nature of it, they were turned from dead Idols, the lying Vanities which they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſerved before, unto the Living and true God to worſhip and ſerve him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By the conſequent of it, which was their waiting for the ſecond coming of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt from Heaven; and he ſhows</p>
            <p n="1">1. The evidence of this ſecond coming, that it will certainly be namely Gods raiſing him from the dead, and receiving him to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ground of their Hope and comfortable expectation, and waiting for this coming in the Text, becauſe this Jeſus had delivered them from the Wrath to come. The wicked (if awakened) do look for Chriſt's ſecond coming with dread and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation, becauſe of the wrath which he will bring with him, becauſe he will come in flaming fire to take vengeance upon them; the righteous (if aſſured of their interſt in Chriſt) do look for Chriſt's ſecond coming with gladneſs and joyful expectation, becauſe he hath delivered them from the wrath to come. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Jeſus who hath delivered us from the wrath to come.</hi> This Doctrine then is plain in the words.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>Doct.</label> That it is Jeſus who doth deliver from the Wrath to come.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In handling of which point I ſhall ſhow,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What this wrath is which is to come.</item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151431:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That this wrath is to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Upon whom this wrath is to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> When this wrath will come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Who this Jeſus is that doth deliver from wrath to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> How Jeſus doth deliver from wrath to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> How any do or may have a ſhare in this deliverance by Jeſus from wrath to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Make ſome uſe and application.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt; What this Wrath is which is to come;</hi> It is not the finite wrath of the moſt furious and feirce Creatures, not the wrath of Lions, or Bears, or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or evening Wolves, or wild Bulls; nor the wrath of the moſt Potent and Tyrannical men, who may exceed all theſe in feirceneſs and cruelty; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it the wrath of the Devil, whoſe wrath is great here on Earth, when let looſe to tempt and deceive, but moſt furiouſly will it expreſs it ſelf hereafter in Hell, when he is let looſe as Gods Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner to torment the wicked: But by the wrath to come, we are to underſtand the Infinite wrath of the Sin-revenging God, in compariſon with which the wrath of all other Creatures in the World is mildneſs, and not in the leaſt to be regarded.</p>
            <p>We read in the Scripture of the Wine of God's wrath, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 10, That this Wine is Red, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. 8. We read of the Viols of Gods wrath, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 1. Of the Cup of Gods wrath, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 10. Of the Wine-preſs of Gods wrath, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 19. We read of the Treaſures of God's wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 5. Of the Veſels of Gods wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22. By the Wine of God's wrath, we are to underſtand thoſe plagues and puniſhments which God doth and will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151431:4"/> inflict upon the wicked for their ſins: By the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Wine is meant the dreadfulneſs of thoſe plagues; By the viols of Gods wrath, ſome ſmaller plagues and temporal puniſhment on Earth; By the the Cup of Gods wrath, eſpecially the dregs and bottom of it, the greater plagues and eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hell; By the Wine-preſs of Gods wrath, we are to underſtand the place where the wicked ſhall be puniſhed; By the Treaſures of Gods wrath the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Plagues; By the Veſſels of wrath, the damned who are appointed to undergo theſe plagues and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; theſe Veſſels God will fill with the Treaſures of his wrath, he will fill them to the Brim in Hell with moſt exquiſite torments; And this is the wrath which is to come, which will be moſt bitter beyond any gall or Worm-wood unto the taſt; which will be moſt pure without any allay or mixture of any comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ingredients; which will be moſt plentiful, the Treaſures of which will be opened in Hell, and all the damned be filled with it abundantly; which will be moſt weighty beyond any Mountain of Lead, to ſink Sinners down into the bottemleſs pit; which will be moſt feirce, and withal ſo powerful, that all the powers of Men and Devils ſhall not be able to make the leaſt reſiſtance; which will be intollerable and yet muſt be bourn; which will be unplacable, ſo as never to be appeaſed, and which will be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſo as never to be ended.</p>
            <p>Plainly the wrath to come, is of the ſame ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the puniſhment of Hell, the great effect of the wrath of God; which puniſhment hath two parts, the <hi>Paena damni,</hi> and the <hi>Paena ſenſus,</hi> the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſſe, and the puniſhment of ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The puniſhment of loſſe, this will conſiſt in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151431:4"/> the loſſe of the Crown and Glory, and happineſs of Heaven, where the righteous ſhall be admitted to the immediate Viſion, and full fruition of God the chiefe good, which will fill them with Soul-raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unconceivable and eternal joy; but from whence all the wicked ſhall be eternally ſhut out, and wholly be denied any ſhare in the leaſt of that happineſs, which when they come to underſtand the worth and excellency of, will above all things be moſt vexatious unto them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The puniſhment of ſenſe, this will conſiſt in the horrible pains and tortures, which ſhall in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity be inflicted upon every part of the bodies of all the wicked, by the moſt dreadful and unquenchable Fire, which they ſhall be thrown into; and the more horrible anguiſh, which through the immediate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impreſſions of Gods wrath, ſhall be inflicted upon every faculty of their ſouls in Hell, where they ſhall have no eaſe nor releaſe for ever, <hi>Matth. 25. 41. Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Devill and his Angels, Rev. 14. 10, 11. The ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his indignation, and ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in the preſence of the Holy Angels, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lamb: And the ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever, and they have no reſt Day nor Night,</hi> &amp;c. See more of this in my Book of <hi>Chriſt's certain and ſudden Appearance to Judgement,</hi> and in my Book of <hi>Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, That this Wrath of God is to come,</hi> this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſeth two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That this Wrath is not yet come</item>
               <item>2. That it will certainly come.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151431:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. This wrath of God is not yet come; were it come, who could ſtand before it? who could deliver from it? where it ſeiſeth it cruſheth, it burneth, and that worſe than any fire; where it ſeiſeth it holds, and never letteth go it's hold for ever; but as yet this is not come, ſome ſparks of this fire may be let fall in temporal judgements upon ſinners in this life, but what are temporal judgements in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with eternal? In this world God doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his patience towards the wicked, he is angry with them, and his anger doth ſmoke againſt them, but he with-holds his wrath from breaking forth into a flame, which would quickly devour all the wicked of the Earth together, ſhould he give way to it, and let it looſe upon them: Indeed we read <hi>John</hi> 3. 36. That the wrath of God abideth upon unbelievers, that is, it ſhall abide upon them, who at laſt are found in a ſtate of unbelief, as ſurely as if it did already abide upon them; or the wrath of God abideth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unbelievers, that is the ſentence of condemnation unto this wrath doth abide upon them, as <hi>John 3. 18. He that believeth not is condemned already.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is ſaid of the perſecuting Jews, who had kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lord Jeſus, and their own Prophets, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the Apoſtles to Preach unto the Gentils, that <hi>the wrath was come upon them to the uttermoſt, 1 Theſ.</hi> 2. 15, 16. But this we are thus to underſtand: that the wrath of God was come upon them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, not in regard of eternal judgements, but in regard of ſpiritual judgements, it being the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expreſſion of God's Wrath, here to give ſinners up unto a perſecuting ſpirit, which doth prepare them for the uttermoſt and moſt dreadful puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hell hereafter. But as yet the wrath of God
<pb facs="tcp:151431:5"/> is not come, none in this world do or can know the power of God's anger.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The wrath of God is to come, that is, it will certainly come, there are ſome things which may come, ſuch and ſuch temporal judgements may come, ſuch and ſuch deliverances may come; but there are ſome things which will come, Death will come, and Chriſt will come, and as certainly as Death and Chriſt will come, ſo certainly this wrath of God will come; God hath foretold it, and Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but not one jot or tittle of what God hath foretold until it be fulfilled: God hath threatned it, and God is not more faithful in his promiſes to his people, than he is true in his threatnings to his enemies. God's juſtice doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to ſend it, which can be ſatisfyed no other way, by thoſe which have no intereſt in the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt. The wicked are Veſſels fitted by ſin for deſtruction, and prepared for wrath, and therefore they ſhall be filled with it, even as the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Mercy are fitted, and ſhall be filled with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: God hath Treaſured up wrath for the wicked, as they have Treaſured up Sin, and God will give them that which they have ſo much deſerved, and he hath prepared for them. However Sinners may eſcape this wrath for a while, and vainly hope to flee or hid themſelves from the ſtrokes of Gods vengeance, yet Gods Right hand will find out all thoſe that hate him, and he will make them as a fiery Oven in the time of his anger, and ſwallow them up in his wrath, and devour them with the fire of his indignation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon whom will this wra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of God come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This wrath of God will come upon all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151431:6"/> of diſobedience, ſee <hi>Col. 3. 5, 6. Mortifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your members, which are upon the Earth, Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, inordinate affection, evil concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſe, and covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry: for which things ſake the wrath of God cometh on the children of diſobedience.</hi> Such are children of diſobedience, who are diſobedient children, ſuch who do nor yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto the Law of God, but live and allow themſelves in the practice of known ſins, and in the neglect of known duties; ſuch who are under the reigning power of ſin, who are willing ſervants of ſin, who yeild up their members as Inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs unto ſin, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 13. Who ſerve divers luſts, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 3. Who make proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14. Such who are Blaſphemers, or Swearers, or Sabbath-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or Murderers, or Adulterers, or Drunkards, or Thieves, or Covetous, or Unrighteous, or Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, or Revilers, or Scoffers at Religion, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Gods people, or have an enmity to the power of Godlineſs; ſuch as are Proud and Boaſters, ſuch as are diſobedient to Parents without natural affection, ſuch as are lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God, ſuch as are Lyars and unfaithful, ſuch as are idle and ſlothful, ſuch as live in envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and are given to revenge, and cannot forgive injuries, and the like ſinners, theſe are Children of diſobedience upon whom the wrath of God will come; ſee alſo <hi>Epheſ. 5. 6. Let no man deceive you with vain words; for becauſe of theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the Children of diſobedience.</hi> Let none deceive you with vain words, neither deceive your ſelves with vain thoughts, as if you might eſcape the wrath of God, although you live in the practice
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151431:6"/> of ſuch and ſuch ſins, ſee how vain and groundleſs the ſecurity of ſuch perſons is, <hi>Deut. 28. 19, 20. Leſt there be among you a root that beareth Gall and Worm-wood; and it come to paſs when he heareth the Words of this curſe, that he bleſſeth himſelf in his heart: ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my heart, to add Drunkenneſs to thirſt: The Lord will not ſpare him, but then the anger of the Lord and his jealouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt that man, and all the curſes that are written in this Book ſhall lye upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name from under Heaven:</hi> Moreover we read, <hi>Gal. 3. 13. Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the Book of the Law to do them.</hi> Such as are guilty of any tranſgreſſion of the Law, (whilſt out of Chriſt) are under the curſe, and lyable unto Gods Wrath, and it is ſaid, <hi>Heb. 3. 2. That every tranſgreſſion and diſobedience received a juſt recompence of reward.</hi> Hence it is that the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience are called children of Wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The wrath of God will come upon all Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, it is more peculiarly appropriated unto them as their portion, <hi>Matth. 24. 51. He ſhall cut him aſunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever eſcape Gods wrath, hypocrites ſhall not eſcape, whoever are pardoned hypocrites ſhall be puniſhed; ſuch as have a form of Godlineſs, but deny the power thereof; ſuch as make ſome ſhow of outward reformation, but are without inward transforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as are like Painted Sepulchres, fair and beautiful without, but within full of rottenneſs; ſuch who make it their great buſineſs to appear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and take no care to be Religious, but are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151431:7"/> rotten at heart and cover carnal deſigns with a cloke of profeſſion; as their ſin is moſt offenſive unto God here, ſo his wrath will certainly come upon them, with the greateſt ſeverity hereafter.</p>
            <p>3. The wrath of God will come upon all impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and unbelieving perſons, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 3. <hi>Except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh, Mark. 16. 16. He that believeth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Repentance and Faith are two great duties of the Goſpel, and wrath is particularly threatned to ſuch as do not obey the Goſpel: to ſuch God will render indignation and wrath, tribulation and anguiſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 8, 9. And Chriſt will come in flaming Fire, to take vengeance upon them, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 8. Such as are impenitent and unbelievers, neglect the Salvation of the Goſpel which by Faith in Chriſt alone is attainable, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the only remedy, they cannot eſcape, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, When this wrath of God will come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The wrath of God will come in part upon the wicked immediately, after the ſeparation of their Soul from the Body, the ſouls of the wicked aſſoon as they are looſned by death from the ruinous Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their bodies, they preſently appear before God, and are condemned to Hell, and dragd by the Devil the Jaylor into that Priſon, where they are bound in Chains of Darkneſs, filled with horrour and anguiſh, until the day of eternal Judgement. The Scripture tells us of diſobedient Spirits thrown into Priſon, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 19, 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Wrath of God will come in full upon all the wicked together at the laſt day, called the day of Judgement and Perdition of the Ungodly, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151431:7"/> 7. When the Lord Jeſus ſhall come to Judge the World, he will bring the Treaſures of Gods wrath with him, and render unto all the wicked that wrath and vengeance which is their due, and therefore this day is called <hi>The day of Wrath and Revelation of the Righteous Judgement of God, Rom.</hi> 2. 5. This will be a dreadful day unto the wicked, when the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and like a Stoll be rolled together, and the Elements ſhall melt with frevent heat and be diſſolved; when the Sun ſhall become black as Sack-cloth of Hair, and the Moon become like Blood, when the powers of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall be ſhaken, and the Stars ſhall fall from Heaven unto the Earth like Figgs from their Tree, when it is ſhaken with a mighty Wind; when there ſhall be Thunderings exceeding loud, and Lightnings and Tempeſt exceeding horrid, when the laſt Trumpet ſhall ſound, and a mighty ſhout ſhall come down from above, and awaken all the Sinners that are aſleep in the duſt; when Chriſt the great Judge of the World ſhall come forth from his Fathers houſe, and make his appearance in the World with Millions of mighty Angels, and all the Saints at his right hand, clothed with Majeſty and brightneſs of Glory; and when the wicked ſhall come forth of their Graves, and ſo ſoon as they ſhall open their eyes, ſhall ſee Heaven and Earth on Fire about their Ears, and the Lord Jeſus coming towards them in flaming Fire to take vengeance upon them; ſo ſoon as they open their ears, ſhall hear the dreadful Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and Shout in the Air, and the Howlings and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of all their fellow Sinners about them upon the Earth, O the dread and confuſion which the wicked then ſhall be filled with! when they are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151431:8"/> ſummoned and dragged to the Tribunal Seat of Chriſt, and there have the Books opened before them, where all their fins are written, and which then will be made manifeſt unto the whole World, and when the Sentence <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting Fire,</hi> ſhall be paſſed upon them, and when the Lord ſhall open the Treaſures of Wrath unto them, and give them that portion thereof which is their due; and when they ſhall ſee the mouth of Hell open beneath them, and an horrible flame iſſuing forth from thence, giving notice of a more horrible fire within, which is prepared for them; O the dread! O the ſhreeks! Who can dwell with ſuch devouring Fire? Who can inhabit ſuch everlaſting burnings? How welcome would a great Rock or Mountain be, if they could find any that would fall upon them, and hid them from the wrath of the Lamb, and keep off the ſtrokes of Gods vengeance, which then will be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them? but the Sentence being pronounced, the Execution will follow, and none can eſcape it; from Chriſt's tribunal Seat the wicked will be rhrown into the fiery Priſon of Hell, where they will be ſhut down, and ſhut in, and that for ever; there they will lye, there they will fry, and there they will cry, and though always dying, yet they will never dye; the fire there will burn moſt dreadfully and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and never be extinguiſhed; and the wicked will be tormented there in every part and in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and their torment will never be ended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, Who this Jeſus is, that doth deliver from Wrath to come?</hi> In the Text he is called Jeſus, and the reaſon of this name we ſhall find, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>Thou ſhalt call his Name Jeſus, for he ſhall Save his People from their Sins.</hi> This Jeſus is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151431:8"/> God and Man in one Perſon; he is the Eternal Son of God of the ſame Eſſence with the Father, equal to him in Power and Glory, who before the world, was appointed in time to be the Redeemer of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and when the fulneſs of time was come, took to himſelf a true humane Body and Soul, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Holy Ghoſt, was Born of a mean Virgin, lived in a mean condition, was owned by a voice from Heaven to be the only begotten and beloved Son of God, who Preached the glad tidings of Salvation to Sinners, confirmed his Doctrine by many Miracles; who died for the Salvation of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and that the curſed death of the Croſs, was raiſed up the third day, appeared to his Diſciples after his Reſurrection, and after forty day in the ſight of many Aſcended up into Heaven, where now he is at the Right Hand of God, making Interceſſion for us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly. How doth Jeſus deliver from the Wrath of God which is to come?</hi> Jeſus doth deliver from the wrath of God which is to come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By his Death,</hi> hereby he hath purchaſed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, having hereby ſatisfied Gods Juſtice; Jeſus in his death did in our ſtead undergo that puniſhment which our ſins deſerved, his Body was nailed to the Croſs, which was a curſed death, and his Soul was afflicted with the immediate impreſſions of Gods wrath, which was ſo weighty and grievous, that any meer creature would have ſunk under it; but he being God-Man did bear up and break thorow, and got looſe from under the burden of wrath, and the bands of death, and the dignity of his perſon put a merit upon his ſufferings, eſpecially the erernal compact or aggreement between him and his Father
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151431:9"/> being ſuch, and ſo became a ſufficient ſatisfaction to Juſtice, and that accepted as fully as if ſinners had done it in their own perſons. We read that Jeſus <hi>himſelf bare our ſins in his own body on the Tree,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 24. That <hi>he gave his life a ranſom for many, Mat.</hi> 20. 28. That we are <hi>Redeemed with his Blood,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. That we are <hi>Reconciled through his Death, Rom.</hi> 5. 10. Jeſus doth deliver from wrath by his death, having therein undergone it himſelf in the room of his People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>By his Interceſſion</hi> Chriſt doth deliver from wrath to come; having offered up himſelf a Sacrifice to ſatisfie Divine Juſtice for ſin, he pleads the merit of it at the right hand of God, in the behalf of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for their Redemption; he is called not only our <hi>Surety</hi> to ſatisfie for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 22. But alſo our <hi>Advocate</hi> to Plead for us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 1. Our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from Wrath to come, the damnation and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Hell doth proceed not onely from Chriſt's death, whereby he hath purchaſed it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from his Interceſſion, whereby he doth effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impetrate and obtain it; and therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth join both together in the procurement of freedom from condemnation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34. <hi>Who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea, rather is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh incerceſſion for us.</hi> And upon this account he is ſaid to be able to Save unto the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Wherefore he is able to Save them to the uttermoſt; that to come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>By his Miſſion, or ſending of his Spirit effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to call People to himſelf</hi> Jeſus doth bring them into a ſtate of Salvation, and giveth them an actual
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151431:9"/> Intereſt in this deliverance, which he hath purchaſed for them, and this leads to the next particular,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly, How any do or may have a ſhare in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance by Jeſus, from wrath to come?</hi> this is by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, which is wrought by his Spirit in effectual calling. When the Lord by his Spirit doth open the eyes of Sinners, and convinceth them of the guilt and evil of their ſins; awakeneth their conſcience, and worketh contrition, and a ſenſe of their miſery and danger; and when the Lord ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and perſwadeth them, how utterly unable they are to Save themſelves, that no reformation or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of their own, which either they have or can attain unto, can procure deliverance from wrath for them; and withal, that no meer Creature in the World is able to help them in this caſe; and when the Lord by his Spirit doth diſcover himſelf, as the only Saviour and All-ſufficient, and moſt willing to ſave and deliver them, and withal doth moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and irreſiſtably, and yet moſt ſweetly how their wills, and encline them to chuſe him for their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and (grieving for ſin and renouncing their own righteouſneſs) to call themſelves, and reſt upon him alone for Salvation, and this accompained with a free, and reſolved delivering themſelves up to his Teaching and Government; this is effectual calling, wherein the Lord by his Spirit doth draw, and lay hold on Sinners, and enableth them by faith to lay hold on him, and hence ariſeth their union to, and Intereſt in Chriſt, and they come to have a ſhare in the deliverance by Chriſt from wrath to come. When the <hi>Jaylor</hi> cryed out with trembling to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas; Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved;</hi> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus, and thou ſhalt be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151431:10"/> Saved, Act.</hi> 16. 30, 31. It is Faith that giveth an Intereſt in Chriſt, and hereby an Intereſt in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, which he hath purchaſed. It is Faith doth unite us unto Chriſt, whereby we are ſaid to be in him, and there is no condemnation to them, which are in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. We are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, And ſo are abſolved from the guilt of Sin, and all obligation unto puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; The Lord Jeſus Chriſt having fully ſatisfied Gods juſtice for our ſins by his death in our ſtead, and this being imputed unto us through Faith, and accounted as if we had done it our ſelves, (as a ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's paying our Debt, is accounted by the Creditor as if we had paid it,) we are acquitted, and no more expoſed unto the wrath of God, and puniſhment of Hell, than if we had never committed any one ſin to deſerve it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Uſe 1. For Information.</head>
               <p n="1">1. See here <hi>the worth of Jeſus,</hi> he is the Deliverer, and the only Deliverer from wrath to come; Jeſus Chriſt is a perſon of the greateſt worth in himſelf; the Divine and Humane Nature, being united in him, rendereth him infinitely glorious, altogether lovely, and hence it is that he is repliniſhed with ſuch tranſcendent excellencies and perfections, as are not to be found again in any. Creature, either in Earth or Heaven; and Jeſus Chriſt is eſteemed to be the moſt worthy perſon, by thoſe that know him and underſtand what real worth is; eſpecially, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners when awakened, and made ſenſible of the curſe which lyeth upon them for ſin, and the wrath of God which hangeth over them, and when they come to apprehend how fearful a thing it is to fall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151431:10"/> under the ſtrokes of Gods vengeance, and ſee no way of eſcape, but only by Jeſus, the only Deliverer from future wrath, of all perſons and things in the World, Jeſus Chriſt is moſt precious unto them; never did there appear in the world a perſon of ſuch high dignity, of ſuch admirable beauty, and ſuch wonderful Love as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who came down from the Father, and clothed himſelf with our nature, for this end, that he might become our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer, our Surety and Advocat, and that he might deliver us from wrath to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. See here the <hi>value of Chriſt's Death; without ſhedding of Blood there is no Remiſſion, Heb.</hi> 9. 22. And if no remiſſion, then no deliverance from wrath to come, if guilt doth remain, puniſhment will enſue, and that of God's eternal wrath in Hell; It was not the blood of Bulls and Goats, Sacrificed under the Law that could remove guilt, and procure remiſſion of Sin. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>For it is not poſſible that the blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away Sin.</hi> But it was through Chriſt's Sacrifice of himſelf once for all, and ſhedding of his blood upon the Croſs, that Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins, and by conſequence this deliverance from wrath to come was purchaſed; It was not thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Rams, or ten thouſand rivers of Oil, or all the Treaſures of the Earth, that could have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red remiſſion of Sin, becauſe all this would have been no ſatisfaction unto Gods Juſtice; but the Blood of Jeſus, who is God-man, hath ſatisfied Gods Juſtice, by his death, Chriſt hath paid the full price, which was due for ſin, ſurely then his death is of greater value, than the riches (were there ſo many) of ten thouſand worlds.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here ſee the <hi>excellency of Faith,</hi> we read in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151431:11"/> firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> of a precious Chriſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 7. And of Chriſt's precious Blood, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 19. And of precious Faith alſo, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 7. Of all other graces, Faith is called precious, and it hath above other graces a peculiar excellency, not in reſpect of it ſelf ſo much, but in regard of it's object, as it doth give Intereſt in the precious Chriſt, and make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his precious Blood, whereby we come to attain a ſhare in this deliverance by Chriſt from wrath to come. Chriſt is moſt precious, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our deliverance; Chriſt death is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as the merit of our deliverance; and Faith is moſt precious, as the inſtrument of our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Here ſee what a <hi>Priviledge it is to have the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Preached amongſt us,</hi> which is a means to make diſcovery unto us of Jeſus Chriſt, the only Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer from wrath to come; as alſo to work Faith in us (which cometh by hearing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17.) Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alone we come to have Intereſt in <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, and his deliverance. Such as are without the Goſpel are in darkneſs and unbelief, and are haſtening for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, towards the regions of eternal darkneſs, and they know not whither they are going; It is of more uſe to have the Light of the Goſpel, than to have the light of the Sun, and the total removal of this light is a greater judgement than any temporal cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſince it is the means to prevent eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 2. For Examination.</head>
               <p>Is Jeſus the only Deliverer from wrath to come? it concerneth all of you them to examine your ſelves, whether you have an Intereſt in this Jeſus, and the deliverance from wrath, which he hath purchaſed,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151431:11"/> and through him alone is to be obtain'd. All of you are Sinners, you were born in ſin, and you have liv'd in ſin, and ſhould you dye in ſin too, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the guilt of ſin doth lye upon you, ſo certainly will the wrath of God come upon you; without an Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt there can be no eſcaping for you; you may know whether you have an Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt by your <hi>Faith,</hi> by your <hi>Life,</hi> by your <hi>Love,</hi> by your <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> and by your <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. If you have an Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, then you have <hi>Faith,</hi> I don't mean an Hiſtorical Faith, only to believe the Hiſtory and report, which the Goſpel doth give of Jeſus Chriſt, what he hath done and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, nor a temporary Faith, which is the food pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of ſome formal hypocrites, whereby they may ſeem to cleave unto Chriſt, when indeed their hearts cleave chiefly to ſin, whereby through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſion of Goſpel Priviledges, and miſapplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goſpel promiſes, they may attain unto ſome kind of fleſhly love and joy, which endures but a while, and they uſually if put upon great tryals do end in open Apoſtacy: But if you have an Intereſt in Chriſt indeed, you have a true juſtifying Faith, whereby being firſt convinced of ſin, humbled and emptied of your ſelves, reſolvedly parting with all your ſins as to affection, and ſincerely renouncing all your own righteouſneſs as to dependance, you caſt your ſelves upon Chriſt, lean and depend upon him, expecting remiſſion and Salvation, alone through his perfect righteouſneſs made yours by imputation. Have you by Faith diſcerned Chriſt? have you by Faith applyed Chriſt? are you by Faith joyned unto Chriſt? have you been by Faith taken off your own bottoms, and built upon Chriſt the chief corner
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151431:12"/> ſtone? have you by Faith been cut off your old Stock, and engroſſed into Chriſt the choice Vine? have you by Faith been divorſed from ſin, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried unto Chriſt the beſt Husband? are you indeed got unto, and into Chriſt by Faith? and have you received him into your hearts by Faith? without this true faith, there can be no true union to Chriſt, without union to Chriſt, there can be no Intereſt in Chriſt, without Intereſt in Chriſt, there can be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, no Salvation and deliverance from wrath to come.</p>
               <p>2. If you have an Intereſt in Chriſt, you have <hi>Life, 1 John 5. 12. He that hath the Son hath Life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life.</hi> He that hath an Intereſt in Chriſt, the Son of God, hath life, he ſhall have Eternal life hereafter, and he hath Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life, which is eternal life begun here; ſuch beſides their natural life, which they receiv'd from their Parents in their generation, they have a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of ſpiritual life, which they receive from the Spirit of God, in their regeneration; they are the only perſons that are quickned from their Spiritual death; but he that hath not the Son hath not life; ſuch ſhall never ſee life hereafter, but the wrath of God abideth on them, <hi>John</hi> 3. 36. And they are ſpiritually dead here, they are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. You may know whether you have an Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt by your ſpiritual Life, I do not ſay by your conſtant livelineſs, this may be wanting at ſometimes in true believers, but you may know it by your ſpiritual life; you were dead, but you are alive; and you may know your ſpiritual life, by your ſpiritual motion from ſin and towards God, by your ſpiritual ſenſes to diſcern between
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151431:12"/> good and evil, by your ſpiritual appetite after Chriſt and his righteouſneſs, and communion with God in his ordinances, and the like; if theſe be no ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of this ſpiritual life in you, it is a ſign that Chriſt is not in you, and if Chriſt be not in you, you have no Intereſt in him and his deliverance.</p>
               <p>3. If you have an intereſt in Chriſt, you have <hi>Love;</hi> you love Chriſt in ſincerity, <hi>Eph. 6. 24. Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity;</hi> and you love Chriſt with the ſupremacy of your love, <hi>Matth. 10. 37. He that loveth Father or Mother, Son or Daughter more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi> If any Man or Woman love any perſon or thing in the world more than Jeſus Chriſt, they are unworthy of him, and they have no intereſt in him, or any of his benefits, and therefore a dreadful curſe is pronounced upon ſuch as do not love Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor. 16. 22. If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha;</hi> that is, let him be curſed until the Lord come, and when the Lord cometh, the wrath of God alſo will come upon him.</p>
               <p>If you have an intereſt in Chriſt, you have <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> you are like unto Chriſt, you have his Image upon you, Jeſus Chriſt is formed in you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 19. You are like to Chriſt in your diſpoſition, in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, meekneſs, Heavenlineſs, and the like; you are not perfectly like to him, yet in ſome meaſure, and you imitate him more and more, and endeavour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more conformity unto his Image; where Pride Reigns inſtead of Humility, where inordidate anger reigns inſtead of meekneſs, where malice and revenge reigns inſtead of Love and forgiveneſs, where the love of the world reigns inſtead of Heavenly minded,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151431:13"/> neſs, where evil concupiſcence reigns inſtead of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified affections, ſuch are without likeneſs to Chriſt, and they are without intereſt in Chriſt, they that are graceleſs, are alſo Chriſtleſs, and they cannot eſcape future wrath.</p>
               <p>5. If you have an intereſt in Chriſt, you have <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> your Faith ſhoweth it ſelf in your works, <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 18. And your love ſheweth it ſelf in your keeping Chriſt's Commandments, <hi>John</hi> 14. 21. Such as do not obey Chriſt's, but caſt his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments behinds their back, and will not that this Lord ſhould rule over them, they have neither Faith, nor Love, nor Life, nor Likeneſs unto Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſure no intereſt in him.</p>
               <p>Try your intereſt in Chriſt the only Deliverer from future wrath by theſe marks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 3. For Reproof and Terrour.</head>
               <p>If upon ſearch, you find you are without an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſt; ſuffer the word of reproof. Sinners what do you think? is there no ſuch thing as wrath to come? is there no ſuch place as Hell, where the damned ſhall be eternally tormented? what black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth is there that dareth to ſpeak againſt this, which is ſo clearly revealed in the Word of God? ſurely none but ſuch as are children of the Devil, the Father of lyes will impeach the Word of God with falſehood, and hereby make God a lyar, who hath foretold this ſo plainly in the Scripture; only ſuch as are looſe in their lives, and deficient in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, whoſe intereſt they think it is to do it, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the puniſhment by eternal fire in Hell, that ſo they might ſin with the leſs check and control; but when they come to feell the heat of this fire, as of all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151431:13"/> others they are moſt like to be caſt into everlaſting burnings, then they will be of another mind. And if there be ſuch dreadful wrath coming, ſuch a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible fire preparing in Hell, for all diſobedient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for all impenitent perſons, for all hypocrites and unbelievers, what do you do ſinners? have ye not ſinned, have ye not by your ſins deſerved? and are ye not by your ſins expoſed unto the vengeance of eternal fire? is there any way for you to eſcape, but only by Jeſus Chriſt the only Deliverer from wrath to come? and yet do you neglect him? do you refuſe and reject him? do you ſhut the door of your hearts againſt him? What! do you mind only your bodies what ye ſhall eat, what ye ſhall drink, and wherewithall ye ſhall be Clothed, and to provide for a ſhort abode in this world, and in the mean time negect the Salvation of your Souls, and take no care to prevent your everlaſting puniſhment? Are you not guilty of a great affront and indignity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, when he hath made ſuch proviſion for your Salvation, as to ſend his Son into the World for you, and to proffer his Son with deliverance to you? don't you ſin againſt his chief command, which is to believe in and accept of this Son? don't you ſin againſt the greateſt impreſſion of his love unto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? don't you ſpurn at his bowles, and in effect ſay, God might have kept his Son to himſelf, for any thing you care? are you not guilty of the greateſt ingratitude towards the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? Never was there ſuch a thing heard of, ſince the foundation of the world; never could ſuch a thing have entred into your thoughts or deſires, as the Lord Jeſus hath freely, and of his own accord done for you; and it is a moſt ſtupendous thing, which me thinks
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151431:14"/> ſhould fill you with aſtoniſhment and admiration, that the Lord of glory ſhould take your fleſh, and make himſelf of no reputation, and humble himſelf unto death, even the curſed death of the Croſs; and all that he might deliver you from the curſe of the Law, the wrath to come, and the pains of Hell for ever; now when Chriſt by his death hath fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied God's juſtice for your ſins, and purchaſed eternal life for your ſouls, and out of wonderful kindneſs hath cauſed the everlaſting Goſpel, and glad tidings of Salvation to be made known in this little nook of the Earth, and caſt your lot in ſuch a ſpot of ground, as the like is not to be found again under the whole Cop of Heaven, for the pure and powerful Preaching of the Goſpel; I ſay, when Jeſus Chriſt hath ſent his faithful Miniſters unto you, (whom you may find and hear if you will look after them) with this Embaſſage, to tell you what Chriſt hath done for you, and to make tenders of him with all his benefits to you; when Chriſt by them lets you know how able and willing he is to Save you, and knocks at the door of your hearts for entertainment; that, though you are ſuch helpleſs and miſerable Creatures without him, you ſhould notwithſtanding all thus refuſe Chriſt or neglect him, that you ſhould prefere ſome baſe luſts before him, and to ſerve the Devil, than to be ſaved by Chriſt; hereby you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs great contempt of Chriſt, and are guilty of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid ingratitude; hereby you trample his Blood under your feet, and you do in effect ſay he might have ſpar'd his pains in coming down from Heaven, that he might have ſtai'd untill he had been ſent for, that he might have carried his Goſpel to any other place, for any thing you value it or him; thus you deal
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151431:14"/> with Chriſt, and thruſt him away from you, though he come upon the moſt welcome errand, and ought to be received with all readineſs and thankfulneſs. And think ſinners moreover how injurious you are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by unto your ſelves, what folly and madneſs you are guilty of; Do you know what you are? if you do, you know that without Chriſt you are curſed wretches, and children of wrath; behold a wonder in Chriſt, everlaſting burnings are become everlaſting mercies, and he that will come at the laſt day as a Judge in flaming fire, to take vengeance upon you, if you be found without an intereſt in him, doth now profer to be your Saviour and Advocat, to deliver you from wrath to come; and is it not depth of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſottiſhneſs to ſlight and refuſe ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and by refuſing him, to plunge your ſelves into unavoidable ruine and deſtruction? when you may have Chriſt, and with him all things needful in this world, and that with greater ſecurity, than by all your inordinate deſires and endeavours; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſuch riches as do exceed all Earthly Treaſures, and beſides this a Crown of glory in the other world, and notwithſtanding this to neglect Chriſt, and chuſe rather the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, the gratifying of ſome baſe luſts unto the everlaſting damnation of your Souls and Bodies in Hell, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe with Chriſt everlaſting happineſs, and head-long to run your ſelves into everlaſting burnings; if this be not folly and madneſs, I don't know what is. You can't contrive or conſult greater miſchief and injury to your ſelves, for I am perſwaded that ſuch as go to Hell out of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially out of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> where they have or might have ſuch plentiful means of Grace, of all others will have the loweſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151431:15"/> and hotteſt place; O how will it ſting, and gnaw, and rack, and torture you for ever, to remember what ſeaſons and opportunities, what calls and invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you have had; but by your right of getting an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus, the Deliverer from wrath to come, you have brought ruine upon your ſelves. Think Sinners, how unavoidable the wrath to come, is without an intereſt in Chriſt, and think, O think, how intollerable this wrath will be when it is come, <hi>Who can dwell with devouring Fire?</hi> Think of the extremity of pain and anguiſh, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you; and think of the eternity of Hells torments, that when you have been there as many thouſand Millions of years, as there are Stars or Sands, your torment will be but beginning, and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Never, Never</hi> will it have any ending; me thinks this ſhould certifie all Chriſtleſs ſinners, who are already condemned to his place of torment, <hi>John</hi> 3. 8. <hi>He that believeth not is condemned already,</hi> and you know not how ſoon execution may follow upon the Sentence, if you dye this night out of Chriſt, the wrath of God will ſeiſe upon you immediately, and you will be miſerable, inrecoverably, and to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 4. For Comfort, and that of all thoſe who upon tryal find well-grounded evidence of their intereſt in this Jeſus, the only Deliverer from wrath to come.</head>
               <p>You are the only perſons in the world, who are in a ſafe condition, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33, 34. Who ſhall lay thing unto your charge? If God do not charge you with guilt, who can charge you beſides? through Chriſt God doth juſtifie you, he pardoneth all your ſins as if they had never been, and accepteth of you as perfectly righteous, through the perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151431:15"/> of Chriſt made yours by Faith. Who is it that ſhall condemn you? the Law may condemn you, and Conſcience may condemn you, but ſince Chriſt died for you, and in his death was condemned and ſuffered in your ſtead, you are freed from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of God, and the eternal damnation of Hell; and being out of all danger of future wrath, you may the better bear any evil of affliction, which in this world may be your portion; and you may comfortably wait for the coming of Chriſt from Heaven, whom God hath raiſed from the dead; even this Jeſus who hath delivered you from wrath to come, and who will bring for you, and give to you everlaſting glory and happineſs at the day of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 5. For Exhortation.</head>
               <p>1. Of ſuch as are without an intereſt in Chriſt the Deliverer from wrath to come; O be perſwaded without any further delay, to flee from this wrath of God, which hath you in the purſuit, and will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you ere long, and that by fleing unto, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an intereſt in this Jeſus, who only can deliver you. O that I might be inſtrumental to bring ſome of you unto a cloſure with Jeſus Chriſt! Sinners will you be perſwaded at length to accept of Chriſt? you may have him, and you muſt have him, otherwiſe you are curſt, you are loſt, and you cannot eſcape eternal death and wrath. If you would be delivered from wrath to come by Jeſus Chriſt, take theſe few directions.</p>
               <p>1. Labour for a thorow ſenſe of your abſolute need of Chriſt, and that not only by reaſon of your guilt of ſin and danger of Hell, but alſo that there is no Salvation nor deliverance attainable by any other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151431:16"/> way but by Jeſus Chriſt: Think not that your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and reformation, though this be neceſſary and without which there can be no Salvation for you, yet that this can ſave you without Chriſt, if you ſhould attain this, and reſt in this, you will as certainly go to Hell, as the moſt wicked tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour; you cannot be ſaved by any of your own righteouſneſs, becauſe your righteouſneſs is imperfect and therefore cannot ſatisfie Gods Juſtice for your ſins, and therefore cannot deliver you from wrath to come; ſhould you weep for your ſins till your eyes were out, and ſigh and grief for ſin till your hearts did break, ſhould your wear you knees to the bones with kneeling, and wear your Tongues to the roots with praying, and conſume your fleſh to nothing with faſting, ſhould you be as juſt, and temperate, and charitable, and as ſtrictly Religious as any breathing; yea, as holy for the future as any Angel in Heaven, all this would not wipe away the guilt of your ſin, nor deliver you out of the hands of Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which muſt be ſatisfied; one ſaith very well, if any would be ſaved by their own righteouſneſs, they muſt firſt go to Hell, and there continue in torments to eternity, and if that could be ſuppoſed, which cannot be ſuppoſed to be done, becauſe there is no ending of thoſe torments which are eternal, and therefore no poſſibility of getting looſe from them, yet ſuppoſing that any could do this, they muſt come back and fulfil the Law in every tittle, both which being impoſſible for you, who are guilty of ſin, you have abſolute need of Chriſt's perfect righteouſneſs in order to your deliverance from wrath to come.</p>
               <p>It is this which damneth and ſinketh many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in Hell, the looking and ſeeking to be ſaved
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151431:16"/> by a rigteouſneſs of their own; I know that moſt are damn'd for their unrighteouſneſs, and go to Hell in the broader way of groſs impiety and wickedneſs; yet if that be the broader way and have it's ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, this is too broad and hath it's thouſands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the more ſober amongſt the Heathens, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived a future ſtate of happineſs, and looked to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to it by the moral Righteouſneſs; beſides the Papiſts, who aſſert juſtification by works, and that we are no otherwiſe juſtified than as we are made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally righteous, and this expreſſing it ſelf in acts of obedience; and beſides Socinians and other Sects together with the Quakers, who plainly affirms that we muſt be ſaved by a righteouſneſs within, which the Quakers call Chriſt within, (all which do funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally erre in their judgements concerning the righteouſneſs, which alone can ſave.) I ſay beſides theſe, it is natural unto all to ſeek Salvation this way; all are born under a Covenant of works, they are under the Law, and not under Grace, and when any think how they ſhall be ſaved, they preſently run to work, and ſeek after a righteouſneſs of their own, and to fulfil the Law themſelves, and hope if they repent and lead a new life, though they have ſinned that God is merciful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and he will pardon and ſave them. It is an ordinary thing, even where the light of truth doth ſhine moſt clearly, and the Goſpel is Preached moſt powerfully, when any are convinced of ſin by the beams of this light, and awakened out of their ſecurity, by ſome powerful Sermon, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their danger of eternal ruine, as the juſt deſert of Sin, they will cry out with the Jaylor what ſhall we do to be ſaved? and however they be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected as he was to believe, yet the moſt do reſt in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151431:17"/> doing and not believing; they fall preſently upon confeſſion of ſin and ſorrowing for it, they fall upon reforming, they will not now be drunk or ſwear, or commit Adultery, or break the Sabbath, or defraud in their dealings, now they begin to hear the Word, and Pray in their Families, and pray in their Cloſets, and keep days of Faſting, and conforms unto all the External acts of Devotion; and if they can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto ſome kind of flaſhy affection, they think all is well; and if they find their hearts dull and cold and hard, they may alſo be troubled for it, not upon a right Goſpel account, but becauſe they feel they want ſuch a righteouſneſs to preſent God withall as they deſire, or through ſome ſecret fear that their righteouſneſs will not hold water; but all this while theſe perſons ſeek after ſalvation through a ſelf righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and Chriſt is left out and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, either unknown or utterly diſregarded and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected by them; and thus many go to Hell in a way of duty, their duties are the occaſion of their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, through their reſting in them, and expecting Salvation by them; It may ſeem ſtrange, that any ſhould have hopes of Salvation by imperfect ſervings, but this I ſuppoſe may come to paſs, either becauſe they don't mind the imperfections of their ſervices, for want of underſtanding the Law in the Spirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, and examining themſelves by it, or through apprehenſions that Gods mercy revealed in his Word will Pardon them, not conſidering that all his ſpecial Mercy, in pardoning and ſaving is through Chriſt; not conſidering that God is infinitely juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as well as merciful, and that there is no room for the exerciſe of Mercy towards Sinners, until Juſtice be ſatisfied; that Gods juſtice requireth a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151431:17"/> perfect righteouſnes, otherwiſe there cannot be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect juſtification, that there muſt be full ſatisfaction to Gods juſtice, for the breach of Gods Law, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there can be no clear remiſſion, and that there muſt be perfect righteouſneſs made out ſome way, otherwiſe we cannot be accepted by God as righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Since therefore this ſatisfaction to Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice cannot be by our ſelves, becauſe being finite, we cannot make an infinite compenſation, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite juſtice doth require, and ſince perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which muſt include both original and actual cannot be in us, who are guilty both of original and actual ſin, and the leaſt ſin rendering for ever a perſonal perfect righteouſneſs impoſſible, and the Law curſeth every one that continueth not in all things, which are written in the Book of the Law to do them, and therefore as many as are of the Law, that ſeeks juſtification and Salvation by the way of works, or righteouſneſs of the Law, are under the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. It is clear that whoever do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be ſaved from wrath to come, it muſt not be by their own righteouſneſs, but by anothers righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, namely the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; If you would attain an intereſt in Chriſt, you muſt be ſenſible of your need of him and his righteouſneſs upon this account.</p>
               <p>2. Labour for a thorow acquaintance with the nature, intendment, and efficacy of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; The Apoſtle ſaith of the Jews, <hi>Rom. 10. 2, 3, 4. I bear them record, they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge, for they being ignorant of God's righteouſneſs, and going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God, for Chriſt is the end of the Law
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151431:18"/> for righteouneſs unto every one that believeth.</hi> And as it was with the Jews of Old, ſo it is with many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Chriſtians now, who may be led only by a blind zeal, to work out their own Salvation in a way of doing, and it is through their ignorance of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, (called here the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God either, becauſe it is the righteouſneſs alone which God, will accept, or which God hath found out and provided for men, which ſence it muſt have, <hi>Rom. 3. 21. 22. But now the righteouſneſs of God without the Law is manifeſt, even the righteouſneſs of God, which is by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. That is the righteouſneſs which God doth accept, and hath appointed for our juſtification; or it is called the righteouſneſs of God, becauſe it is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, who is God-man, no other righteouſneſs than of ſuch a perſon, being ſufficient for man in his fallen eſtate;) I ſay through the ignorance of this righteouſneſs of Chriſt, many Chriſtians ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a righteouſneſs in order to their Salvation, they go about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, that is a perſonal righteouſneſs, and endeavour the gaining of Heaven in a way of doing, and ſo do not ſubmit themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God; It is through Pride (ſo natural unto every one) that they are loth to be beholding wholly unto another, and therefore they would have ſomething of their own to commend them unto God, and therefore they do not ſubmit unto the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which God hath provided for them.</p>
               <p>Therefore you muſt labour to be clear in your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, what this righreouſneſs of Chriſt is; there are two things requiſite and abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto fallen man. The firſt is ſatisfaction unto
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151431:18"/> Gods Juſtice for his ſins, and without this there can be no eſcape of eternal death and miſery, becauſe guilt doth oblige unto puniſhment, and this cannot be removed until Gods Juſtice be ſatisfied; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect actual obedience unto Gods Law, and without this there can be no attaining eternal Life and Glory: the firſt Covenant of works, (ſo Man in his fallen State) being ſtill in force, <hi>Do this and Live,</hi> and the Soul that ſinneth ſhall dye; now man being finite, cannot ſatisfie Gods juſtice for his ſins, and being a Sinner, cannot yield perfect actual obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods Law; but the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath done both for man.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt by his ſufferings, and death upon the Croſs did make ſatisfaction unto Gods juſtice, he being made a curſe for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing equivalent puniſhment, puniſhment unto the damned storment, and being God-man, though the humane nature only did ſuffer, yet the Divine nature in the ſame perſon did put an infinite value upon the ſufferings of the humane, and ſo became a ſufficient ſatisfaction unto Gods infinite juſtice, and hereby he hath purchaſed remiſſion of ſins and deliverance from wrath to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt hath yeilded perefect actual obedience unto the Law, he hath fulfilled all righteouſneſs, that not having a righteouſneſs perfect of our own, his might he made ours, and we might attain life thereby; this paſſive and active obedience of Chriſt which you ſhould labour to underſtand, and that Chriſt had not this righteouſneſs for himſelf, he had no ſin of his own to ſuffer for, but it was in our ſtead, and as our ſurety, and this righteouſneſs was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us, and being the righteouſneſs of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151431:19"/> is highly efficacious to attain, that for which it was deſigned, as will appear by the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Labour for a thorow underſtanding of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and that both the Covenant, which God made with Chriſt in the behalf of man, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which God hath made with man through Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Acquaint your ſelves with the Covenant God made with Chriſt, in the behalf of man, whatever worth and value there was in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, yet God might have required a perſonal righteouſneſs and ſatisfaction, and Chriſt's righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs might have ſtood us in no ſtead; but God did eternally Covenant and agree with Chriſt, that if he would take Humane nature and work out a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for fallen man, it ſhould be accepted, that if he would take to him the body, he ſhould prepare for him, and make his Soul an Offering for ſin, that is, ſuffer what his juſtice did require for the ſins of Man, that he ſhould ſee his Seed, and juſtifie many, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 10, 11. It is through this Covenant with Chriſt that Chriſt righteouſneſs is accepted in the behalf of Sinners, God having agreed before that, ſo it ſhould be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Acquaint your ſelves with the Covenant God hath made with Man through Chriſt, wherein upon the account of Chriſt God hath promiſed remiſſion of ſins, and eternal life, <hi>Heb. 10. 16, 17. This is my Covenant that I will make with them ſaith the Lord; I will put my Laws into their hearts, and their ſins and iniquities I will remember no more. 1 John 2. 25. This is the promiſe which he hath promiſed, even eternal life.</hi> If ever you be ſaved from eternal wrath, and attain eternal life, it muſt be by vertue of this New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151431:19"/> of Grace, wherein God doth engage himſelf to give what his Son hath purchaſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Labour to be acquainted with the nature and uſe of faith, which is the Tenour of the Covenant of Grace; the Tenour of the Covenant of work was <hi>Do and Live,</hi> the Tenour, or that required to give an intereſt in the Covenant of grace is <hi>Believe and Life;</hi> Faith joyns the Soul unto Chriſt, the Mediatour of this Covenant; and giveth an actual intereſt in him and his purchaſe, and whatever is promiſed through him in the Covenant; Faith is a reſting of the Soul alone upon Chriſt, and an application of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Pardon and life unto the Soul; Faith is not only a diſcerning, but applying or laying hold on Chriſt's righteouſneſs without us, whereby it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, or accounted once by God, as if it had been our own perſonal righteouſneſs; If ever you would be juſtified, that is, have your ſins pardoned, and your perſons accepted as perfectly righteous in the ſight of God, it muſt be by Faith, renouncing your own righteouſneſs as imperfect and inſufficient, apprehending and applying, reſting and truſting in Chriſt's perfect righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Apply your ſelves unto God in Prayer, that he having given his Son for you, would alſo him give to you, and that he would give you Faith to receive him, and apply him; beg this again and again, with confeſſion of your ſins and ſenſe of your want of Chriſt, and never leave asking until you obtain; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend alſo upon the Word where it is Preached moſt purely and powerfully for the working of Faith, which cometh by hearing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. And then in the ſtrength of the Lord put forth the hand to lay hold on Chriſt, and labour to caſt your ſelves upon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151431:20"/> him, reſigning withall, your ſelves up unto him, not only to be ſaved, but alſo taught and ruled by him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> I know it will be objected, that if we ſeek thus to be delivered from wrath to come by Jeſus Chriſt, and Faith in his righteouſneſs without us, and not by internal righteouſneſs, and that of works, that this will open a door to Licentiouſneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I Anſwer, That this is an old Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Doctrine of juſtification by Faith, even in the days of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when the Doctrine was firſt Preached. But as then, ſo alſo now this Doctrine doth not give any liberty to ſin, for however we cannot be ſaved by inherent righteouſneſs, and any of our good works, yet we cannot be ſaved without them; none aſſert more highly that there muſt be Regeneration and Sanctification, a new heart and new life, otherwiſe there can be no admiſſion into Heaven, no eſcaping of the damnation of Hell; Yea, further we ſay that the ſame Faith which is an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of juſtification, is alſo a part of Sanctification, being a heart purifying grace, <hi>Act,</hi> 15. 9. That as Faith is a hand to lay hold on Chriſt's righteouſneſs without us; ſo it is a hand to receive ſupplyes of grace and ſpirit from Chriſt for the quickning of us unto newneſs of Life; yea, I may ſay there can be no real inherent righteouſneſs, withou an intereſt by Faith in Chriſt's imputed righteouſneſs, there may be ſome thing like it, a righteouſneſs of ſome kind there may be, but not of the right kind, not a righteouſneſs which ſprings from the true principle, which is ſaith, and therefore not a righteouſneſs that is pleaſing unto God, for without Faith it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. So that if you would have inherent righteouſneſs, and walk ſo as to pleaſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151431:20"/> God, you muſt belive in the Lord Jeſus, and fetch grace from him, in whom all fulneſs doth dwell, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 19. If you would have luſt mortified, the world crucified, and overcome the Devil, who endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by his temptations to draw you unto ſin, you muſt by Faith draw vertue and ſtrength to do it. In a word, if you would deny Ungodlineſs and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, and live ſoberly, righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent evil world, you muſt do it by Faith. But how to attain the principle and practice of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I may elſe where give direction.</p>
               <p>Had I room I might ſpeak much by way of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to ſuch as have attained an intereſt in Chriſt, and the deliverance purchaſed by him; in a word, learn to admire free grace, to be very thankful and watchful, to endeavour the bringing others to Chriſt, to adorn your profeſſion, to be blameleſs and harmleſs the Diſciples of Chriſt, without rebuke in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation, among whom you ſhould ſhine as Lights in the World here, that ſo you may ſhine like Stars, yea, like Suns in the Kingdom of your Father for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:151431:21"/>
            <head>Books of this Author Printed.</head>
            <p>God's Terrible Voice in the City; <hi>being a Re-Plague and Fire in</hi> London.</p>
            <p>Chriſt's certain and ſudden appearance to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven, <hi>in the Burning of</hi> Sodom <hi>formerly.</hi> From Earth, <hi>in the Burning of</hi> Aetna <hi>lately.</hi> In Hell, <hi>to Burn the wicked eternally. Theſe Printed for</hi> George Calvert, <hi>and to be Sold at his Shop at the Golden</hi> Ball <hi>in</hi> Duck-lane.</p>
            <p>Words <hi>whereby we may be</hi> Saved, <hi>and</hi> Words of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to young Men. <hi>Printed for</hi> T. Parkhurſt, <hi>and to be Sold at his Shop, at the Golden</hi> Bible <hi>on</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-Bridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Foundation of God Standeth Sure, <hi>or an Anſwer to</hi> W. Pens Sandy Foundation Shaken.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
